this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software as a software engineer chances
are you've crossed paths with MongoDB at
some point whether you're building an
app for millions of users are just
figuring out a side hustle as the most
popular non relational database MongoDB
is intuitive and incredibly easy for
development teams to use now with
MongoDB Atlas you can take advantage of
MongoDB flexible document data model as
a fully automated cloud service MongoDB
Atlas handles all the costly database
operations and admin tasks you'd rather
not spend time on like security high
availability data recovery monitoring
and elastic scaling try MongoDB Atlas
for free today visit MongoDB comm slash
cloud to learn more this is Nate black
for software engineering radio my guest
today is Boris journey the author of
programming typescript Boris is the
organiser of the san francisco
typescript meetup and is a software
engineer at Facebook Boris welcome to
software engineering radio thanks mate
for having me on I want to start with
just talking about what typescript is at
a high level what is typescript the
typescript it's it's a really really
weird language that works exceptionally
well in practice unlike a lot of
languages it's compiled but the compiled
target is very high level so it actually
compiles to JavaScript it has a really
cool type system you can describe the
type system in a bunch of ways but I
guess at a very high level it's
structural static strong mostly inferred
and gradually typed the gradual typing
part is also pretty unusual there is
maybe a small handful of languages
around that our graduate I pits it's
really thing from the last 10 years or
so
I think typescript is the most
successful out of those always so far is
typescript popular or how does it
compare to the alternative compile to
JavaScript options that are out there
it's surprisingly hard to come by
numbers there's the survey called state
of j/s it seems like it's grown
something like 50% year-over-year
and if you go by NPM the downloads have
increased something like three times
you're over your overall if you're
looking at this pace of compiled 2gs
languages which is really interesting
space and I think it kind of deserves
its own conversation about why are there
so many compelled to GS languages the
typescript is by far the biggest so
judging by the number of type
definitions that are available for
third-party libraries as of a year ago I
think it was something like 10x bigger
then flow which was the next closest one
and that's bigger than you know reason
closure script scholar J s all of these
other compelled to J's languages why are
there so many of these what why is it
needed to have a compiled to j/s
language I think it surprised everyone
how big JavaScript got you know it's
it's really the scripting language and
for some reason now it can run on every
computer on every phone you can run a
little VM on IOT device or on a
Raspberry Pi to run it it's so
ubiquitous so people have built this
really big apps on it Facebook has built
some really big applications on at
Google has built really big applications
on it a lot of people really rely on
JavaScript but the problem is it's sort
of a weird we design language and it has
a ton of different foot guns and it
lacks some of these fundamental features
like static types that people typically
talk about as being necessary to scale a
program across more engineers more
devices etc so I I think people saw all
these different thorns and JavaScript
and all these different limits to
scalability and try to solve it in all
these compelled to J's languages and the
advantage there is there's this enormous
space of devices that can already run
JavaScript so all we have to do is write
something that can compile the
JavaScript and then it can already run
in these devices you don't have to
convince people to install your VM or
install a binary or anything like that
goo created typescript or who's behind
it and maintaining it yeah so tips group
it's a project at a Microsoft it's
created by Anders Hallberg it's the same
guy that did c-sharp he also did some
work on the mono runtime he did some
other famous projects it I think there's
also contributions from a lot of open
source people from Google Google's of
the
dr. so there's some contributions there
but it's it's mostly out of Microsoft
does that mean that there are some
similarities to c-sharp or if a person
knows c-sharp or perhaps Java how far
away are they from understanding how to
use typescript yeah I think it's pretty
similar at least at least as far as
appearances go I'm not a c-sharp guy
I've written a little bit of Java but
I'm no expert at it but at least if you
if you look at the language the syntax
is certainly similar to c-sharp
conversely on the other side of things
how similar or dissimilar is typescript
from JavaScript yeah so typescript
compiles the JavaScript and it
interoperates really well with
JavaScript and that actually goes pretty
far actually to the point where every
valid JavaScript program is also a
typescript program it might not type
check but it will compile so for example
if you have a JavaScript file ends with
a s rename it to a dot TS extension
that's a typescript program how well
does it work together with something
like react or angular it works really
well
the typescript works well with whatever
framework you might be using angular
written in typescript it works well with
Emperor with view my favorite
combination personally is react and
typescript because with react you
express the view as JSX
which is kind of this representation of
HTML in your JavaScript it's nice
because this elevates the view code to
values and because their values that
means you can now model it with types
and this is a as opposed to you know
these like older view systems stuff like
handlebars or you know these other
systems where essentially your view is a
big string and use these templates to
template in values in the problem there
is it's not really typesafe but because
you when you use react with typescript
because the JSX is a value you can use
typescript to make all sorts of
assertions about it and prevent you from
doing invalid stuff so an example is
let's say you have an unordered list in
your view and you have some list items
within it you can enforce that the only
valid child of an unordered list like a
UL tag is an li tag and this is
something that you get for free when you
use typescript with react actually don't
know if it enforces this constraint in
particular but there is a lot of similar
constraint so you can enforce these kind
of parent-child relationships
you can enforce that if you instantiate
a component it must be given particular
props of a particular type so it's a
really nice combination for react react
native angular all this stuff and pretty
much works out of the box what kind of
projects do you think can benefit the
most from typescript yeah so personally
I use typescript for everything
everything from you know the smallest
projects little scripts and stuff like
that this gives me a little bit more
confidence that they're gonna work when
I run them all the way to the biggest
projects so typescript is used
internally at Microsoft at Google swak
so really big companies it kind of gets
to the core of of gradual typing and I
think we're gonna talk more about this
later but kind of this trade-off between
typing things dynamically and tipping
them statically and both have their use
cases I think I think the bigger your
project is the more benefit it will get
from typescript but I use it for
everything is that why the subtitle of
your book is called JavaScript that
scales what does it mean to scale in
this case so I think it means a couple
of different things so one is it will
scale across more lines of code another
is it will scale across more engineers
in another one it'll scale across more
devices so taking that one one at a time
so more lines of code if you have a
bunch of code so you have a big code
base you know if you're a big tech
company of millions of lines of code
maybe a little bit smaller and you have
tens of thousands or hundreds of
thousands at some point your code is
gonna start breaking when you start
making changes to it and the reason is
it's not totally clear when you modify
something what else it's gonna affect
and static types really help solve that
problem so they give you a certainty
that when you modify a line of code or
the API to some function or some kind of
module you know exactly what else it's
gonna break at least for certain classes
of errors
it also helps go across more engineers
so it's documentation when you add
little type annotations to function so
you know you have a function f it
accepts a number and returns a string
that's a form of documentation for the
function in a replaces some dock box
they might be writing and then the last
one is it'll scale across more devices
because once you start scaling to
services and start writing
multi-threaded JavaScript you very
quickly run into the
we're unless you have well-defined
protocols your your communication might
break so one device might send a message
making one set of assumptions a
different device might be on a different
version or make a different set of
assumptions and it might not quite work
altogether so typescript is one of many
tools that lets you type both sides of
that communication which helps give you
more confidence about any kind of
protocols when you say skills across
platforms what's an example of that
let's say as an example you can write
type scripts that runs on your browser
you can also write typescript that runs
on the server let's say no js' in that
case if you had a function and the API
in your node.js application that you're
calling from the web application you
could have more confidence that you're
using the right set of parameters
because you had the type information on
both sides is that right yeah that's
exactly right you there's a bunch of
tools that do this but at a high level
typically how it works is either you
have a common source of truth that you
compile bindings for for both the client
and the server or for multiple servers
or you have a source of truth on the
server that you then compile bindings
for for the client so instead of kind of
independently writing API endpoints on
both sides so on the server let's say
you implement a rest endpoint on the
client you make some assumptions about
the parameters that endpoint accepts
instead you're going to compile a
function you're going to generate a
function for the client set that you can
then call it's important to note
typescript itself doesn't do that
compilation so it's not going to take
your server-side endpoint and compile
points that code for it automatically
but there's a lot of tools that do it in
one way because we're targeting
JavaScript
typescript is kind of a natural language
to express this kind of contract in I
want to move on to how typescript works
and this gets back to what you said
before about how typescript compiles to
JavaScript but you also mentioned that
JavaScript can be run through the
typescript compiler and I was always
under the impression that javascript is
an interpreted language but it sounds
like that's a mistaken assumption can
you explain how the the compilation
process works and what walk us through
what the
typescript compiler does yeah let's
maybe take a step back first if that's
okay and talk about JavaScript a little
bit so the way JavaScript works is
JavaScript is also javascript is an
interpreted language but that doesn't
mean that if you write some JavaScript
code put it in a text file feed it into
your browser or at a chrome and then and
then run that JavaScript it's not just
literally running that code there's a
bunch of steps in-between this is
something that's changed a lot over the
years it depends on the exact top form
that you're running on but say you know
v8 or some other browser or some other
engine but between being a text file and
actually being run by the browser
you're gonna compile it to bytecode or
you might compile it to machine code so
there's still this compilation process
it just happens in a lazy way where you
don't do it ahead of time but you do it
right before the user actually executes
the program with typescript this stays
the same in kind of the beauty of
typescript is it's one of these
languages that targets JavaScript
there's many languages that do it
typescript is just one of them but
because of the targets JavaScript you
can run it on any platform that supports
JavaScript and the way that typescript
does it is it takes code and then it
outputs JavaScript code which you
thicken you can then run as you would
have run before you wrote that changing
type definitions of a typescript program
won't change the compiled JavaScript
output how is that possible and what
does that mean exactly
yeah this is really important to forming
a good mental model of how typescript
works so typescript is just JavaScript
plus some types the types will never
affect the output of the program so you
can fiddle with the types all you want
you can make it safer you can make it
less safe by using different kinds of
types but in the end the genes-- that
generated JavaScript output will look
exactly the same
if for example I I had a typescript
program that defines some some types
like let's say I defined some some some
classes and then changed the definition
of those classes but it continued to
compile then you're saying that the
generated output would be identical yeah
that's exactly right so the types effect
type checking that the types
empower does before it compiles but
either way it can still compile your
code even if it doesn't type check even
if the types don't totally work it can
still compile of course if you want to
off opt into more safety typescript has
a whole bunch of different safety flags
one of them is a fog that controls this
behavior and will not emit code unless
the program type checks that part is
actually the most difficult part for me
to understand how it can compile the
code even if it doesn't type check maybe
you can't roll into that a little bit
more yeah I think the key inside here is
that the types will never affect the
generated output so it doesn't matter
what the types are they could be
complete gibberish they shouldn't be
because that's kind of giving up some of
the benefits of typescript but whatever
the type started the program will still
compile so the typescript looks at the
value level of your program as opposed
to the type level so essentially the
JavaScript part of it not the typescript
part in order to compile it the types
are just used for type checking which is
the step it does right before it
compiles it if the type checker is
giving me some information that it
didn't type check correctly it's still
compiled but it was telling me that it
thinks there's an error in my program
then what's the step that I would take
or how would I respond when you write
typescript you're gonna get errors right
in your text editor
assuming that editor supports typescript
I think this is every big editor out
there so vs code Adam sublime text as
you type you got little red squigglies
right in the IDE warning you that you
made a mistake and as an engineer
there's different ways that you can
configure your project I recommend in
most cases setting up your project in
such a way that unless there are no red
squigglies the code doesn't compile so
you should really listen to the type
errors because they're pointing out very
likely mistakes in your program that you
should probably fix but if you want you
can you can ignore them so as an
engineer if if there are any kind of
errors in your program it's gonna be
surfaced right as you type code so as
soon as you take the error you're gonna
get a little red squiggly underline
under that error in your IDE and then
you can fix it on the spot I want to
move into typescript paradigm what is
the big idea or
paradigm behind typescript I think the
big idea behind typescript is that the
types are there when you need them and
they get out of the way when you don't
need them
typescript supports all sorts of
different paradigms of programming you
can do functional programming you can do
object-oriented you can do in period of
programming you can let typescript infer
all the types for you where you can
specify them explicitly it's sort of up
to you and typescript interoperates with
javascript it works well with all of
these styles of programming I think the
idea is that the types are fun and
they're useful in that it shouldn't be
tedious to fix them if we want to
understand types and typescript what's
the best place to start is its
structural typing is it classes or where
do you want to begin with that I think I
would maybe start with a high-level
overview of the the type system itself
so maybe what are the how does the type
system work and then what are the kinds
of types that the typescript supports so
typescript it's a fully structural type
system I think as you're Westerners know
this is as opposed to a nominal type
system different languages are split on
this some languages are a mix of
structural and nominal some are fully
nominal some are fully structural so
typescript is almost fully structural
and the reason it does this is because
javascript is fully structural too so
you have a JavaScript function it takes
maybe a few different types of arguments
and you don't really know what you're
gonna get before him so one thing you
might do is check arguments and you
might have you might inspect it and you
might say if the arguments a number do
this if it's a string do this
and likewise it may be if the arguments
an object you might check some fields on
the object to see if they exist if some
set of fields exist to this otherwise do
this other thing because this is so
common in JavaScript the way to model
this with static types is with a
structural type system in it works
remarkably well in practice the second
part of that is that typescript tip
system is static which means that
verification of types happens at compile
time that's before you actually run the
program so in in just raw JavaScript you
can add runtime type check so you can
say if the type of this thing is a
number then proceed otherwise throw a
runtime exception
with typescript these kind of errors are
surface to compile them so you for
example if you have a function you
specify the types of arguments if the
actual arguments that you pass don't
match those types that's an error at
compile time so that means you don't
actually have to run your program to
know if you did something wrong the
other the other aspect of the type
system is that it's strong so in that
strong as opposed to weak it's not a
value judgment about the type system all
it's saying is that for example in
JavaScript if you try to add an array
and a number the result might be a
string because javascript is trying to
do the best I can to coerce the types at
runtime to match the intention you had
as a programmer so maybe as a programmer
you mistyped something javascript is
gonna try to do its best to make sure
that works
Ted Script isn't quite as flexible
because if you're adding a number an
array that's very likely mistake so the
typescript takes the opposite approach
where tries to catch these kind of
mistakes as early as possible and that's
why we call it a strong type system the
other part is that is inferred so
there's very few things in typescript
that you have to specify explicitly if
you have a function in the tend the
function has parameters the parameter
types you have to type explicitly most
things other than that are inferred so
for example function return types the
types of local variables all of this
will be inferred by typescript in your
book you talked about a concept called
assign ability is that something related
to static type checking or typescript
being strongly typed yeah it is so let's
do a let's do like a hello world of this
so yeah you have a function f it takes
some argument that's a string and you
call F with a number what should happen
here if this was JavaScript JavaScript
would try to do the best again and it
would take this number and proceed as if
you didn't pass a number because it
doesn't know any better
but with typescript if you imitated the
parameter as a string and you passed a
number typescript is gonna perform a
sign ability check so it's gonna check
hey is that number assignable to a
string number and string are types that
are not related so it's gonna fail says
can be a little red squiggly in your
text editor as you typed it saying hey
you you pass the number did you mean to
pass a string
on the other hand in most cases it's
it's gonna work because you did the
right thing so if your function takes a
string and you pass it a string that's
gonna work correctly you explained that
in typescript types exists in a
hierarchy and at the root of this
hierarchy is a type called any what's
the role of the any type yeah that's
right so they're there step called any
in typescript any you should try to use
as little as possible it's essentially a
trapdoor typescript gives you a ton of
these trapdoors so if you don't want to
write the perfect program you don't want
to think through the types right now you
can just mark something as any type and
that'll let it through so again going
back to the the world simplest function
it's a function that accepts a number
and you pass it some kind of value of
type any that'll be okay in general you
should try to avoid it and again
typescript has a whole bunch of comp our
settings that'll be on this kind of
behavior for you and in any big codebase
you should avoid this and you probably
should be on this kind of stuff but
otherwise there's a whole bunch of an
ability rules that typescript checks
when it decides is something assignable
to something else so essentially when
you expect some kind of value is it okay
to pass this other value in most of the
time it's pretty intuitive so if you
have a function that expects let's say a
number or a string and you pass it a
string that's okay cuz the string is a
number or a string but on the other hand
if you expect a boolean you can't pass
it a class anything like that
you mentioned gradual typing and that
typescript is it gradually typed the
language please explain gradual typing
yeah gradual typing it's this idea that
your program might be composed of code
at different levels of safety so some of
the code might be totally untyped so no
meaning no static types at all and then
some of the code might be totally
covered with types so no any is nothing
like that the compiler knows all of the
types at compile time I was researching
a little bit I think one of the first
languages that are gradually taped to
his ActionScript and that's a thing goes
back in 1998 and a week the guy that
works on flow which is another compiled
two gs language he actually worked on
ActionScript back in the day in addition
to ActionScript there's a bunch of these
Ling
that are gradually typed so the Google
closure is an example typescript
obviously hack out of Facebook is
another one of these and from what I
could find these graduated languages
mostly come out of really really big
companies they have really big code
bases like millions of files and I think
it comes out of this practical thing
where you find yourself in a situation
where you have a big javascript code
base and you're not quite sure what to
do with it because initially it was
really nice to have everything in
JavaScript because it meant that you can
move really fast and you can iterate
quickly because you didn't have to wait
for a type-checking to happen you didn't
have to add types to everything but at
some point it became a liability because
it not having these types also meant
that you could you can't iterate as
quickly anymore and now when you make a
change you have to be so careful not to
break anything else you have to make
sure to write a ton of unit us to do QA
to smoke test your app and I think it
also meant that it's hard to scale
across a lot of Engineers so these big
companies found themselves in a place
where they had these existing really big
code bases it wasn't practical to
totally rewrite everything at once but
it was really really important to get
more safety because it became liability
and that's I think where these Roger we
typed link we just came from so
typescript is a really great example of
it but again it's it's one of a few and
it's a it's a really modern phenomenon
let's go back to this idea of structural
typing if I define a function as
accepting a certain type you said that
because typescript is is structural I
think that applies that I can give that
function another type that doesn't have
the same name but it would still be
accepted by the compiler as a valid
argument is that true
yeah I think that's a good way to think
about it the mental model is if you need
some type any type that behaves the same
way is okay it doesn't have to share the
same name okay so if it had to share the
same name that would be nominal typing
versus structural yeah and it actually
goes pretty far so maybe one of the
unintuitive bits of typescript
is if you have a function that needs
some kind of class within instance of
Class A that has a few members on it
and you pass that function at instance
of Class B that has the same types of
numbers on it so the same fuels with the
same types on those fields that's okay
by typescript because like javascript
javascript is duck typed so typescript
tries to inherit this behavior and it
tries to model that statically duck type
being if it looks like a duck walks like
a duck and quacks like a duck it's a
duck write in a language like Java or C
sharp you would have to have some kind
of interface and you'd have to say that
both of those types shared the same
interface and the function accepted a
type of that interface in order for that
to work but in typescript you don't need
to explicitly declare that they share
the same interface that's right it could
be good practice for documentation for
other engineers working on your code
base to make a shared interface anyway
but it's it's really up to you if
there's no if there's not going to be a
behavior at runtime typescript isn't
gonna complain about it the typescript
tries really hard to complain about
things that would be real errors and to
stay out of your way if you're doing
something even if it's a little bit
weird but that wouldn't result in an
error what is type refinement type
refinement is a really interesting
behavior of typescript its typescript is
one of a small handful of languages out
there today that that have this kind of
behavior I think the best way to think
about it is to start with an example so
let's see let's you have you know back
to this function f it accepts either a
number or a string and the way you
indicate that in typescript is using a
union type so it looks like number pipe
string that's how you're gonna annotate
that in a function and then inside of
the body of the function what say you
want to do different things depending on
if the argument was a number or a string
and the thing that you would do in
JavaScript is use a type of check so if
argument if typeof argument equals
equals and then number in quotes do this
otherwise do this in typescript is smart
so it understands this at compile time
and it knows that in the body of that if
function the argument must be a number
and if there is a return statement it
implies that outside of that if function
after that function or after after that
if block the argument must be the other
type it's a pretty convenient behavior
in a way to model a lot of Java
Script isms so a lot of JavaScript ppis
are designed in this way where something
might be a union of things and you kind
of as you process this thing you're
gonna refine it and depending on what
type it actually is you might have a
different behavior let me just double
check my understanding you're saying
that even if I declare my function to
take a less specific parameter in your
example a union type as I progress
through my function the compiler can't
actually know that in a later block of
code it's definitely a more specific
type and from that point forward it can
treat that variable as that more
specific type right so just as a
programmer reading here that functioned
you understand intuitively that if
you're doing a type of or instance of or
in check inside the block it's gonna be
one type not the union of all the
possible types typescript understands
that too so it tries to encode this
intuition in the type checker itself is
that information something that is only
relevant or only available at compile
time or or is that some how can that
also be made available at run time and
is there any use for that yeah so
something like a if you're using a type
of check for example this is something
that will be available at runtime
because type of is a runtime operator
it's it's just a regular JavaScript type
of check so if you have if typeof
argument equals equals number then do
something that code will remain after
typescript compiler program because this
is value level code there's there's
actually no types in there because
you're comparing the the type of the
argument to it to a string so it's
either the string string or the string
number because it's just a JavaScript
check typescript is smart enough to
understand it but this code will remain
in place after you've compiled it okay
but would I be able to would I be able
to use user defined type from typescript
at runtime so for example if I'd defined
type foo what I'd be able to do a type
of foo and compare or
is that not available at runtime that's
a good question so all the types in
typescript are stripped away as you
compile so after you compile none of the
type information is left so if you used
let's say the type keyword to define a
type a away as for foo this would not be
available at runtime so you mentioned
that type aliases and we talked about
classes so these are all these are both
examples of of types what's the
difference maybe we can get into like
what's the difference between what's a
type versus a type alias versus an
interface how are they related they have
and how are they different yeah so going
back to what I was talking about before
I mentioned type level in value level
earlier some parts of a typescript
program are written at the type level
and some of them are written at the
value level value level is it's all all
the parts of the program that valid
JavaScript code that's those are values
these are things that exist at runtime
as you run your program these are things
that exist in memory everything else is
only used at compile time there's a
bunch of things that are only used at
compile time in typescript and these
things are created using the type
keyword the interface keyword and then
there's a few other ways to create types
so you mentioned in classes classes
declare types but they also declare
values so if you have a class a that
creates two types actually so generates
a type for the instance of the class a
they could then use to type a function
let's say you have some function that
needs an instance of a if you use the
class keyword to create a you know class
a and then that has some methods has
some properties etc you could then use a
directly in that functions parameter
list so you can say you have you know
some function f and it takes some
argument of type a and that means the
instance of class a and then we use the
class keyword the other thing that it
creates is all the static members so if
you had some static methods on the class
you can retrieve that using again the
type of keyword so typescript kind of
reuses this type of keyword so you can
fetch that again is it just a difference
in the way that you declare a type or
are there different kinds of types
whether it be a Enter
face type alias or a class in typescript
you can express a whole bunch of
different types so you know just you
know a little laundry lists you can do
number string boolean you can do arrays
tuples classes objects and all of these
there's different ways to express them
in the type system in order to express
them you can either declare it in line
or you can name the type so that you can
reuse it across multiple places and it's
sort of similar to how in JavaScript you
you would use a value inline or you can
send it to a variable so you can
reference that variable for multiple
places so there's different ways to
create a type in typescript you can
declare it inline you can use the type
operator to make a type alias you can
use the interface keyword to create an
interface or you can use a class which
will also create a type all of these are
pretty much interchangeable and
depending on what you need and depending
on the type of class that you need you
can use the appropriate one let's say
you have a function f and it needs some
class a so one thing that you can do is
you can use the class keyword to declare
a class so class a and the little curly
bracket maybe set implements and
properties implements and methods and
then you would say you would declare a
function f whose argument is of type a
the other thing that you can do because
type typescript is structure we types it
thinks about classes a little a little
bit differently so what is the class
it's a thing that can be nude neew nude
so you can make a new instance of this
thing so the way this works is let's say
you have this function f and it takes
some argument you can say the argument
is something that you can call that you
can new and that'll return an instance
of a having played around with
typescript a little bit what I noticed
you can do is you can declare a function
and the function has a parameter that
has some kind of structure let's say
it's an object it has a string property
and number property you can just declare
in the Declaration of your function you
can just give it something that looks
like bracket foo colon string bar colon
number
and that's good enough then basically I
can give that function any argument with
it with that same shape exactly and then
if you if you want to reuse that same
shape in a different function if you
want you can pull it out just like you
would pull out a variable in JavaScript
and the way you can do that is there's
kind of two ways so one is you can use
the type operator so you can say type my
object equals curly foo colon number
comma bar colon string and then you can
update your function to say this
argument is of type my object and
equivalently you can use the interface
keyword instead of the type keyword to
do the same thing so you can say
interface my object curly Foucault and
string bar colon number and it'll work
the same way
how would you consider the choice
between the type alias the first way and
the interface that the second way like
what would cause you to choose one or
the other you think they're very similar
there's a few very nuanced differences
in practice pick the one that you like
stylistically the best I personally
prefer the type keyword I know some
programmers that prefer the interface
keyword because they're coming from oo
languages the type keyword does give you
some options like you can't do a I think
an intersection or a union of different
types is that is that something that's
available on for interfaces as well or
is it limited just type aliases so the
something like that is limited to a type
it with an intersection if you're not
familiar with it it's a let's say you
have to object types you know a and B
one object type has one member food
that's a number the other one has a
number bar that's a string in
intersection of those would be an object
type representing foo number bar string
so an object that has both properties
defined so with the interface you could
also express this and the way you would
do that is using the extends keyword so
you would define an interface for one an
interface for and then an interface for
the other one that extends that first
one and that's in practice it's very
similar to what the intersection
operator would do which looks like an
ampersand
there's some things that you can't
express using interfaces so this is
unions for example aliases to primitive
types so for example let's see of a type
a equals number so it's just something
that used for readability or for
documentation you can't do that so
interface is just for object types where
would the union of two types be useful
likewise it would be an example this is
something that comes up fairly often in
JavaScript let's say you're defining a
jQuery API I don't know if anyone used
uses jQuery nowadays but let's say you
have a jQuery API and it's animation API
and it takes some options and let's say
either you can pass it a single number
representing the duration of your
animation where you can pass it an
object with some more details and let's
say that object can have a property
duration that's a number and type that's
a string and when user jQuery plug-in
you can use either one of those so you
can either pass a number or you can pass
this options object and at the type
level in typescript we would represent
this as a Union so you would say it's
number pipe and then this object type
with Curly's okay so it gives you some
flexibility and saying I can accept
something that looks like this or like
that yeah that's right so if as you're
explaining this to yourself or you know
to another programmer if you do if you'd
use the word at work you sometimes a
union can be a good way to model that
another type of structure that you deal
with a lot in JavaScript is JSON and
that seems to be an something that other
type systems struggle with at least in
my experience it's difficult to work
with JSON in Java for example how easy
is it to work with with JSON can you
impose some type of type safety on it
when you're when you're processing
something like JSON yeah so as long as
you've typed your API you're gonna get
the types for free so I talked about
this a little bit earlier but there's
all these there's a few different tools
that you can use to generate these type
safe API is for you which essentially it
will generate typescript code for you
which then makes sure that the API is
type safe
of course if you're using just raw JSON
so it's a like the fetch API or
something like that you can just cast it
to the correct typescript type and from
then on it's totally safe
so you've carved out this little unsafe
island and everything outside of this
island is really safe as long as you've
done a good job of typing this boundary
than the rest of its going to be safe
you know of course JSON it supports a
lot of the same types that typescript
does so you can model objects arrays
strings numbers billions all this kind
of stuff in typescript it's super
succinct there's one little feature that
was convenient I thought in JSON you
have a lot of properties but you can
actually say something mean of
meaningful about the the key in the
property can you explain how that works
or maybe I'm not using the right
terminology but there was this that's
that little bit of syntax that that
makes it convenient for working with
properties yeah so if you have a JSON
object there's some properties that it
might have and with some api's it might
also take additional properties that are
optional so you might say that there's a
you know property a that's number maybe
a property B that's a string and then
any number of other properties that are
boolean and that's totally okay in
typescript so you can model that using
an object type and then something called
an index signature that models these
additional types of properties and then
the typescript also has operators to
model optionality so if the field may or
may not be defined all of the stuff that
you might see in JSON you can model
using typescript
type system and it's really built for
objects so it can model it really
succinctly I want to talk about
interoperability between typescript and
JavaScript
what more can you say about
interoperability yeah so in modern
JavaScript programs you're going to be
using a whole bunch of code right and
this is it's often a criticism of the
JavaScript ecosystem but it's also kind
of nice javascript is a very modular
language so something that you might do
is you might have a bunch of first
pretty code and then you might also
install a bunch of stuff from NPM so a
bunch of third-party packages some of
these packages might be written types
your code may or may not be typescript
it might also be a mix of JavaScript and
typescript
so when typescript was designed this is
one of the use cases it had to support
this is so common in JavaScript programs
that it'sit's really important to be
you'll be able to use whatever packages
you want in for it to work correctly and
if these things were written in
typescript then you also get the benefit
of type checking you get nice auto
completion in your text editor all of
that comes for free so the way
typescript works is you can use
JavaScript from typescript and by
default when you import a JavaScript
module in typescript it's any and if you
don't want any x' in your program so
personally i don't you know what a big
code bases again like at google
so use a typescript compiler file to
bend us so what you do is you create
this thing called the type declaration
and essentially it's like a header file
for the javascript package and it models
the outward interface of this package
for most third-party code that you might
use it's already available so there's
this namespace on NPM called add types
and usually what you can do is let say
you install would say blow - you can
then do NPM install at types slash flow
- and that will install all the type
declarations for lodash - so you can
then use it safely from typescript you
can also write these type declaration to
yourself in the rare case that it's
missing
but typescript is such a big ecosystem
you're probably gonna find it already
but sometimes you don't want it
sometimes you're just prototyping some
something really fast maybe you're using
some really exotic package that no one
has written type declarations for yet so
what you can do is you can just turn off
the safety flag in the typescript
compiler import this package and use it
it's gonna be any so you're not gonna
get the benefit of static type checking
we can quickly prototype stuff is there
a way to isolate those parts of the code
that are that have less strictness or
maybe where you don't have the type
information available yeah you can
certainly do that typescript is built to
be practical so one of the things that
you might do is you might want to
interoperate with JavaScript code you
might even start with JavaScript code
and then gradually migrate the code base
to typescript and this is a really
common pattern this is something I've
done that house companies I think a lot
of people that are switching to
typescript are gonna be in this boat
where you have a big JavaScript code
base
and you know one piece at a time you're
going to move it to typescript so the
way that works is you just rename your
file type a TS extension it can still
use JavaScript and that's okay and what
you can do is you can opt that part of
your codebase into these strong safety
guarantees so for typescript files don't
allow any x' but then for JavaScript
files you're importing it's okay to have
any x' for example and over time as you
migrate more and more of your code you
might want to flip on these safety
settings one by one there's like dozen
or so fogs for safety to make your code
more and more restricted and you have
stronger and stronger guarantees that
you're doing the correct thing at
compile time would one approach to this
be if you had a not necessarily a really
large program but a sizable enough
program that you could break it into
modules would it be useful to put stuff
that wasn't type checked into one module
or let's say you had some dependencies
you didn't have type information for
could you isolate that into one module
and then just export some type of type
safe interface to import and the other
part of your program yeah that's
certainly something you can do I think
it will depend on your particular code
base most often actually I'm not sure if
I've seen people do this module based
approach I think usually your other code
is just J's files and the code that
you've migrated is dot TS but it's all
part of one code base but certainly if
you want you can split your code into
modules and then have different levels
of safety for each or even migrate a
module at a time but I think the more
typical path is migrating just a file at
a time but at the project level you can
only have one setting for compiler
options like whether or not you'll allow
any so then if you don't modularize
there's a trade-off in how much
strictness you can apply to the project
overall yeah I think that's a good way
to think about it at its core typescript
is a gradually typed language what
graduate typed means is the language
might have zero types or it might be
fully types and these things have to
play together they have to interoperate
but if you have untyped code in your
system it limits the overall safety of
your system so you might it might not be
as safe at compile time as it might be
if all your code was tactically typed
but this is one of the nice things about
typescript is that you can migrate a
piece by piece and then once you've
migrated everything or the critical mass
of your code you can turn off these you
can turn on these stricter settings to
enforce that things are correct at
compile time in episode 248 axel Roush
Meier on JavaScript and equi script six
we talked about how some existing tools
like babel can compile one version of
javascript into another can you please
explain how these other tools coexist
with or can be used together with
typescript yeah so typescript those two
things it's a compiler and it's also a
type checker the type checking is
something that only typescript can do
the compilation is something that other
tools like you mentioned babel they do
it too and compilation is something like
you have yes 2018 JavaScript or 2019 and
you want to compile it down to let's say
es6 javascript so older browsers or
maybe a older node.js runtime is going
to support it you can do that with
typescript compiler itself for bigger
projects I recommend is using babel
there's a couple different types script
plug-ins for babel so you can just plug
it into your existing setup and it'll
just work does that mean that i i don't
explicitly run the typescript compiler
but that's something that babel takes
care of as part of his process yeah
that's right there's a few different
plugins so there's a few different
approaches to it i think the the typical
setup is you're gonna use the babel
plugin it's gonna run both type checking
in the compiler for you in parallel to
speed it up a little bit so you're still
gonna get the benefit of red squigglies
in your text editor when you do stuff
that's invalid but then babel stole
handles compilation like it did before
is there any other topic that you wanted
to cover that we didn't talk about yet
maybe one is null as a type I think
that's somewhat unusual so everyone's
heard this famous quote that Knoll was
the billion dollar mistake the the
problem is no is a type it's it's a
value it's also a value that a variable
can be but it's something that
remarkably few type systems model at the
type of all some things might be
knowable some things might not be
knowable and it's important to handle
the cases where they might be no
that's often a runtime exception so in
Java that's you know a
nullpointerexception
so in typescript null is actually a type
so you can say a value is either a
number or no or we'll see of a non
nullable value you can say it's just
always a string and it's important to
make this distinction because if
something can be no it's really
important to handle it in type scribble
verify at compile time that you've
handled all the nulls does that mean
that if I declare function with
parameter type string and then I try to
pass a null it's gonna fail at compile
time unless it can verify that that that
value is definitely not no yeah that's
right or if you have a function that's a
string or no it's okay to pass it a
string or no when you say string or null
is there special syntax for that or we
just have to be the type alias or
interface would have to say that it was
string or null with like a Union
notation yes it's a union notation so
it's a string than the pipe character
then no that remind me of something that
I read somewhere that the majority or
maybe even the vast majority of runtime
errors in JavaScript are type errors
does that mean that the goal in a sense
is to get rid of like eliminate that
class of errors is that what ultimately
you're trying to do with with typescript
I think that's right there's a you know
as a programmer you have limited time in
the day and there's all this code you
have to write and we're just human so we
make a whole bunch of mistakes and some
of these mistakes are easy to identify
some of them are a little bit harder
they might be architectural issues that
you know take a design review and you
know it takes sitting down with your
team to really walk through and
understand so typescript prevents the
really dumb mistakes it's the mistakes
that could have been caught a weren't
because you weren't using types and it
makes it super easy to do that good I
think that's a good place to wrap things
up just for final thoughts for our
listeners I wanted to make sure that we
said something about your book could you
please tell us about your book sure so
it's called programming typescript its
O'Reilly first book about typescript
been working on it for the last couple
of years mostly night
weekends I'm pretty proud of it so check
it out it's on Oh Riley books also on
Amazon it's definitely worth checking
out is there any other resource or a
place where listeners can't find out
more about you and the work you're doing
I would check out github so in github
I'm at B journey Dec HDR and why if you
also want to learn more about typescript
without paying for the book
check out the typescript handbook it's
pretty good but if you really want to go
into depth it suggest you check out the
book great thanks Boris thanks for being
honest up for engineering Radio thinking
it for software engineering radio this
has been Nate black thanks for listening
thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
at SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening